Guide to the records of the Musical Acoustics Research Library (MARL) M1711
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Musical Acoustics Research Library (MARL)
1956-2007
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hutchins,, Carleen Maley
Benade, Arthur H.
Coltman, John Wesley
Backus, John, 1911-1988
Catgut Acoustical Society
M1711
59.39 Linear Feet (138 manuscript boxes, 3 card boxes)
The MARL collection is dedicated to the study of all aspects of musical acoustics. The collection, established in 1996, came about through the joint effort of the representatives of the Catgut Acoustical Society (CAS), founded by Carleen M. Hutchins and devoted to the study of violin making; Stanford’s Center for Computer Research in Music Acoustics (CCRMA), and Virginia Benade, the widow of the wind instrument acoustician Arthur Benade. MARL consists of the research materials from acousticians around the world who were dedicated to studying different aspects of violin making, which make up the Catgut Acoustical Society papers, and the archives of three prominent wind instrument acousticians of our time, John Backus, John W. Coltman, and especially Arthur H. Benade, which deal not only wiht wind instruments, but also room acoustics, and the interplay between acoustical physics and the mechanisms of auditory processing. The collection consists of papers, photographs, media, digital materials, wood samples, clarinet mouth pieces, and lab equipment
Access to Collection
Open for research. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy. Most unpublished materials in this collection have been digitized, except for personal correspondence which has not. The digital surrogates may be accessed via the links that accompany the description in the container list.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in four main series: Series 1: Catgut Acoustical Society Collection (including John Backus papers); Series 2: John W. Coltman Collection; Series 3: Arthur H. Benade Collection; Series 4: John Backus Collection.
The original holdings of the Arthur H. Benade Collection increased during the last two years (2009- 2011) since new materials were donated by Arthur Benade's widow, Virginia Benade. Gaps in the numerical order of boxes is due to materials that were added to the collection at later dates.
Scope and Content
The MARL collection includes: correspondence, published and unpublished papers, detailed laboratory notebooks, photographs, meeting reports, miscellaneous writings, slides, sound recordings of acoustical experiments, samples of woods and varnishes, various designs of violin bridges, and a collection of different wind instruments’ mouth pieces.
Music -- Acoustics and physics.; Wind instruments.; Stringed instruments; Musical instrument makers; Musical instrument building; Room acoustics; Auditory processing; Young, Robert W.; Worman, Walter Elliott; Vogt, Walter W.; Weinreich, Gabriel; Hutchins,, Carleen Maley; Schumacher, Robert T. (Robert Thornton); Bodley Bessaraboff, Nicholas; Shankland, Robert S.; Benade, Arthur H.; Stetson, Karl A.; Coltman, John Wesley; Sundberg, Johan; Schaeftlein, Jürg; Raman, Chandrasekhara Venkata, Sir; Bell Telephone Laboratories; Saunders, Frederick A. (Frederick Albert); Schelleng, John C.; Groupe d' Acoustique Musicale; Roederer, Juan G.; Rosenberg, Ellis; Dayton C. Miller Flute Collection; McClain, Ernest G.; McIntyre, Michael; Fryxell, Robert Edward; Leipp, Emile; Bate, Philip; Jansson, Erik V.; Backus, John, 1911-1988; Hartmann, William M.; Meinel, Hermann; Lottermoser, Werner; Jameson, George; Kent, Earle L. (Earle Lewis); Pasqualini, Gioacchino; American Association for the Advancement of Science; C.F.Martin Co.; Bucur, Voichita; Backhaus, Hermann, 1885-1958; Catgut Acoustical Society; Fox, Sidney; Condax, Louis M.
- Series 1. Catgut Acoustical Society Collection, 1963-2007; 24.186 Linear Feet
  - Abbott, John A. - Correspondence, 1962-1990; A1333-101 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence: (1962-1990) between CMH and John & wife Doris. Miscellaneous: Newspaper obit.
    Biographical / Historical
    John Abbott, a chemical engineer, known for his role in development of food freeze-drying processes, introduced himself to CMH after reading her first article in Scientific American. As an active amateur violin maker, he subsequently obtained her advice on plate tuning & the use of willow for liners in the instruments he was constructing. He and his wife, Doris, were good friends of the bowmaker, John Bollander, with the result that his interests shifted to research on bows. This activity led to the articles included herein, final preparations for which were assisted by his son as he raced against time in his fight against terminal cancer.
    Abbott, John A.
  - Abbott, John A. - Technical Ms., 1954-1990; A1333-102 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Technical: Manuscripts regarding papers on John Bollander; includes correspondence regarding publication in CASJ and to Bollander from Abbotts. Topics: Bow dynamics; Bollander, John; Mahogony for frogs
  - Abbott, R. B. - Response Measurement and Harmonic Analysis of Violin Tones, 1935; A1335-101 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Technical: A 1935 JASA paper on violin tones. Topics: response measurement; Harmonic analysis
    R.B. Abbott worked during the l930s on methods of testing violins and published at least one paper, included here. He went to F.A. Saunders to discuss his methods and ideas, but Saunders did not wish to collaborate.
    Abbott, R. B.
  - Abild, Robert - Correspondence, 1971-1984; A1485 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Topics: restoring violins, violas, cellos, and basses
    Abild, Robert
  - Ågren, Carl Hugo - Miscellaneous, 1966-1982; A2775-101 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    A Swedish engineer who has worked with the instruments of the viol family for many years. He developed and made a slightly enlarged version of the treble viol. In the process of this he worked with K.A. Stetson on the interferometric holograms of the viol plates, braces and all, photos of which are in the file. See the JASA paper on this. He also developed a moire method of visualizing the arching contours of viol and violin plates which can be quite helpful in getting the arches symmetrical. See CASNL article on this.
    Correspondence; Biographical sketch; Interview with Agren, 1969
    Ågren, Carl Hugo
  - Ågren, Carl Hugo - Correspondence, 1966-1982; A2775-102 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence: (1966-1982) mainly with CMH.
  - Ågren, Carl Hugo - Technical, 1969-1976; A2775-103 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Technical: 8 papers from 1969-1976; 4 papers, 3 drafts, and 1 magazine article (1969). Topics: Hologram interferometry | Electronic plate tuning | Technology and viols | Resonance measurement
  - Allen, Mildred - Correspondence, 1963-1986; A4270-101 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    A Professor of physics at Mount Holyoke College who, in her retirement acted as secretary to F.A. Saunders who had moved to South Hadley for his retirement years. When Saunders died she collected all his research equipment and turned it over to the CAS. Through 1986 she continued her interest and membership in the CAS and always sent us a Christmas card of her beloved collie.
    Correspondence: Christmas cards and letters to CMH 1963 - 1986. Technical: Paper from Am J of Physics, 1963, on conductivity of Germanium crystal. Topics: Germanium crystal
    Allen, Mildred
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Members of the CAS participated in several symposia on musical acoustics at the annual meetings, 1971 and 1975 particularly. The 1971 meeting was organized by A.H. Benade and included a demonstration concert of the Octet instruments. The 1975 meeting was part of "Science for the Naked Eye" set up by Rolf Sinclair (NSF), which included a demonstration of the Octet by William Berman, Chris and Michael Finckel and Diana Gannett Mizelle with CMH talking. Walter Sullivan attended and gave us a fine write up in the New York Times which would have resulted in a NOVA TV show except that we did not have a full octet performance group available. CMH was elected to the Nominating Committee for Physics B, and made a Fellow of the AAAS.
    Correspondence on AAAS meetings
    Correspondence: (1971-1975) primarily about the Dec. 1971 and Jan. 1975 AAAS meetings. Correspondents include: A.H. Benade, William Berman, Norman Edge, Daniel W. Haines, CMH, Rolf M. Sinclair, Raymond J. Seeger and W. Dixon Ward.
    American Association for the Advancement of Science -- Archives
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Miscellaneous, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    AAAS Philadelphia Meeting 1971
    Miscellaneous: Dec. 1971 Meeting in Philadelphia. Program, notes, and handout. Session 1(A H Benade): Acoustics of Orchestral Musical Instruments - draft of paper by CMH - "Violin Family Instruments" Session 2(W Dixon Ward): Musical Perception - draft of paper by Boomsliter & Creel - "Toward a Theory of Melody".
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    AAAS New York Meeting 1975
    Miscellaneous: Jan. 1975 Meeting in NYC: programs of sessions, abstracts, illustrations, conference brochures, full texts of papers, news clipping, and notes about instruments from the New Violin Family to be taken to the meetings.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between AAAS and Hutchins
    Correspondence: (1975-1981) between CMH and AAAS primarily with Rolf Sinclair regarding Nominating Committee for Physics Section B. Also an invitation to speak at 1980 meeting in Chicago (declined). Miscellaneous: Review in Science (1985) by CMH of "The Science of Musical Sound" by Pierce, J. R.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - Miscellaneous, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    AAAS Washington Meeting 1978
    Miscellaneous: Conference brochures, programs, and handouts, etc. 1977-1988.
  - American Society for the Advancement of Violin Making - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    The idea for this society came from Dr Albert Kaplan, a retired psychologist, who had contacted a group of his friends, including Mr Sidney Fox, an engineer with Bethlehem Steel and an avid chamber music player. It is reported that their initial meeting was in the shop of William Moennig & Son. Fox, who had purchased one of Hutchins violas, wrote to her in 1971 at the Catgut Acoustical Society suggesting that we meet with Kaplan to discuss the need for such a society. This meeting at 112 Essex Avenue resulted in Fox and Hutchins making a survey of the violin making schools in both the USA and abroad. Hutchins felt that such a school should be connected with a broader education than just violin making as is the case in both Cremona and Mittenwald. Kaplan wanted a separate school. After several more discussions and efforts to locate possible sources of funds, Kaplan and his group decided to found the American Society for the Advancement of Violin Making. The information in this file gives a brief survey of this development and the subsequent change in name to the Violin Society of America.
    Corresp: (1971-1975) between CMH and Ray H Abrams, Eric Chapman, Edward Durnall, Sidney Fox, Albert J Kaplan and Elizabeth McGilvray. The corresp is from the early years of the ASAVM before it changed name to Violin Society of America.
    American Society for the Advancement of Violin Making -- Archives
  - American Society for the Advancement of Violin Making - Miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Flyers; business cards; brochures; announcements; book review by Nick Stamon on Goodkind, Herbert K. "Violin Iconography of Antonio Stradivari."
  - Anderson, Walter F. - Correspondence, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondence: with CMH 1966 - 1972; Newspaper clip on appointment as Dir. of Music Programs for NEA 1968; Vita; an NSF grant proposal for violin making at Antioch College.
    A pianist and organist (F.A.G.O.) and a composer with a wide experience in teaching music to various groups (see bio). He was much interested in the work of the CAS and the development of the Octet instruments. At the time he worked with us he was Director of Music at Antioch College. He participated in a grant proposal to N.S.F. with H.T.E. Hertzberg and H. von Gierke for "Applying acoustical physics to the construction of stringed instruments" which was not funded. Subsequently Andy was made Director of Music Programs for the National Endowment for the Arts (1968).
    Anderson, Walter F., 1915-
  - Antioch College - Violin-Making School Proposal, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    In the early 1960s Edward Hertzberg came to 112 Essex as a result of the SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN article by CMH. He became very much interested in the research and developments in violin making that were going on and saw the need for further work along these lines. In subsequent conversations with CMH, Hertzberg developed the idea that Antioch College would be a good place for such a program which would give it a center and the possibility for some real funding which CMH was unable to get because the foundations she had approached indicated that one person working in her own cellar was not a good risk. The resulting grant proposal to the National Science Foundation is included here and indicates the scope and personnel involved. Hutchins felt that the grant was overstated and too costly. Some of her reactions to a meeting with the group at Antioch are included here. The grant was not funded. The CAS continued to pursue its own course at 112 Essex and in the next few years managed to do the work projected in the grant without extra funding.
    Misc: unsuccessful grant proposal (1966) for the establishment of violin-making at Antioch College; magazine article on Antioch; NY Times article on Sloan grant; CV and publications list for Henning Edgar von Gierke. Corresp: with CMH and Dean of Faculty Albert B Stewart, Academic VP, Morris Keeton; Notes by CMH before and after meeting 11/30/66 in Yellow Springs. Topics: Grant proposal; Violin school
  - Applebaum, Samuel - Correspondence and Misc., 1957-1976; A6480-101 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    A famous string instrument pedagogue, known throughout the USA and abroad, who gave hundreds of string clinics, many of them sponsored by the American String Teachers Association, largely for teachers and high school students. With the help of his wife, Sada, Applebaum published manuals for string teachers and orchestra directors "Building Better Strings and Orchestras", "Applebaum String Method", "The Best of Sevcik", etc. For a biography, see included article "Teacher's Teacher", American String Teacher 1969. He is best known to musicians for the series of books "With the Artists" by Samuel and Sada Applebaum, John Markert, N.Y. (Also, "The Way They Play"). The Applebaums lived in Maplewood, not far from Montclair. We saw quite a bit of them and they were always most supportive and helpful in publicizing the CAS. Their son is Michael Tree of the Guarneri Quartet.
    Correspondence: (1957-1976) with CMH. Some letters by his wife Sada. Miscellaneous: News clipping, ASTA magazine article, & String Tones Tribute to Applebaum.
    Applebaum, Samuel
  - Applebaum, Samuel - Publications, 1955-1965; A6480-102 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Publications: Tutors in string playing (5) and assorted publishers' flyers to works by Applebaum (one of the flyers is for joint publication with his wife, Sada).
  - Arns, Ulrich - Correspondence, 1957-1974; A7670-101 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    A student of Herman Backhaus in Karlsruhe who went on with research of vibration patterns in violin plates and finished instruments, and published several papers, one of which is included here. He was especially interested in the concept that certain parts of the violin top and back contributed to different tone ranges.
    Correspondence: with CMH (1974). 1 technical paper (1957) on objective testing of the violin.
    Arns, Ulrich, 1925-
  - Askenfelt, Anders G. - Correspondence, Misc., 1982-2001; A8345-101 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between CMH, Anders Askenfelt, and Eric Jansson
    Askenfelt, Anders
  - Askenfelt, Anders G. - Publications, 1979-1999; A8345-102 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Babitz, Sol - Correspondence and Misc., 1964-1968; B1140-101 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    A fine cellist and an early proponent of the instruments of the viol family, who was especially interested in the renaissance, baroque, and transition instruments of the violin family. See article in THE STRAD included here. He was fascinated with our Octet instruments and wanted CMH to make him a violino piccolo with five strings (which did not happen).
    Correspondence: with CMH 1964-65. Technical: From Strad, 1964?, "Identifying the Renaissance, Baroque and Transition Violins"; Miscellaneous: Flyer from Early Music Laboratory 1968; Recommendation for Guggenheim Fellowship by CMH 1964
    Babitz, Sol
  - Backhaus, Hermann - Correspondence, 1972-1973; B1260-101 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Worked in Germany for many years on the acoustics of the violin, first at Greifswald and later at the Technische Hochschule in Karlsruhe. His unique contribution was the first mapping of the vibrational modes of the arched top and back of the violin, vibrated with an automatic bowing device at main resonance frequencies. His most important conclusion was that a strong tendency exists among the best instruments for the inward and outward motions of the top and back plates to be in phase over a large area of the violin at some frequency near 700 Hz. At lower frequencies he found far more subdivisions to occur. Backhaus' pioneering work together with that of his student, Hermann Meinel, has provided investigators with much basic information. See Backhaus papers in Benchmark Papers in Acoustics, Volume 6, Dowden Hutchinson and Ross 1976.
    Correspondence: (3) about Backhaus (1972-1973); to & from Springer-Verlag and CMH; from Hermann Meinel to CMH (translated by J.C. Schelleng)
    Backhaus, Hermann, 1885-1958
  - Backhaus, Hermann - Miscellaneous, 1958; B1260-102 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Miscellaneous: (2) Obituary notice of Backhaus (1958); other miscellaneous biographical material.
  - Backhaus, Hermann - Technical, 1925-1938; B1260-103 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Technical: 9 papers from 1925-1938; some have abstracts. Topics: Bowed string | Wolf-tone | Radiation properties | Nodal patterns | Violin acoustics
    Gap in box numbering
    For box 4 and folders 1-4 of box 5 see Series 4: John Backus Collection
  - Backus John - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Barducci, Italo - Miscellaneous, 1948-1974; tk471fr1040 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Physicist working in many fields of acoustics at the Instituto di Acustics O.M. Corbino of the Italian National Research Council, starting in 1943, whose findings are contained in 65 papers. His primary connection to musical acoustics is his collaboration with G. Pasqualini on the first definitive study of wood for violins "Misura dell' attrito interno e della constanti elastiche del legno" which can be found in Benchmark Papers in Acoustics v 5, Dowden Hutchinson and Ross 1975.
    Miscellaneous: (4) Biog; Correspondence: between CMH and Barducci (2:1972-1974); Tech paper on wood with Pasqualini (partial translation). See Tech Summary. Topics: wood.
    Barducci, Italo
  - Barton, Edwin - Technical, 1910; yh614xf5295 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Professor of Experimental Physics, University College, Nottingham whose paper with Thomas F. Ebblewhite "Vibration Curves of Violin Bridge and Strings", Phil. Mag. 20 456 4 (1910) is one of the first such studies. Apparently C.V. Raman worked under Ebblewhite before he went back to India and did his own research on the bowed string.
    Technical: "Vibration Curves of Violin Bridge and Strings" from Phil. Mag 20 pp.456-464, 1910 by Barton & T.F. Ebblewhite Topics: Bridge motion | String motion
    Barton, Edwin H. (Edwin Henry)
  - Beauchamp, James - Correspondence, 1968-1987; sb633nm9810 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    A research engineer-acoustician, originally in the Department of Speech at Stanford University, and since 1970 working at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, who has done and continues to do analysis and synthesis of violin tones. Two of his early papers are included here. His most recent one (at this writing) was given at ISMA '92 in Tokyo: "Investigation of timbre using spectral modeling and interpolation."
    Correspondence: between CMH and Beauchamp; also corresp referring Ronald B Standler to Beauchamp (1968-1987).
    Beauchamp, James W.
  - Beauchamp, James - Technical, 1965-1974; gg669vb5990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Technical: 3 papers from 1965-1974. Topics: Computer analysis | computer synthesis | Violin tones | Harmonic analysis
  - Beldie, Ion Paul - Correspondence, 1965-1991; B4270-101 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Physicist, a native of Romania, MS from University of Bucharest, Doctor of Engineering under L. Cremer at the Heinreich Hertz Institute, Berlin. Especially interested in wood technology and musical acoustics, Beldie's work includes studies on the Chladni patterns in violin plates as well as the characteristics of resonance spruces related to the criteria needed for violins. He also studied the low frequency radiation of the violin (see Benchmark Vols. 5 and 6 and CASNL).
    Correspondence: between CMH and Beldie (1965-1991); from Kathie Hildebrand (cousin of Beldie) to CMH.
    Beldie, Ion Paul
  - Beldie, Ion Paul - Miscellaneous, 1967; B4270-102 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous: biog material on Beldie and N. Ghelmeziu.
  - Beldie, Ion Paul - Technical (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bell Labs - Correspondence, 1961-1986; B4340-101 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between CMH and Joe Kohut, Ruth Schyu, Pierre M. Ruiz, Jean-Claude Risset, and Max Mathews
    Bell Telephone Laboratories
  - Bell Labs - Miscellaneous, 1962-1966; B4340-102 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Bell Labs News for release. Voiceprint, unique as a fingerprint.
  - Bell Labs - Technical, 1966-1969; B4340-103 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Papers (3): Jean-Claude Risset and Max V. Mathews. Analysis of Musical-Instrument Tones; Roger N. Shepard and J. Douglas Carroll. Parametric Representation of Nonlinear Data Structures; Roger N. Shepard. Extracting Latent Structure from Behavioral Data
  - Benade, Arthur Henry - Correspondence, 1961-1987; B4560-101 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Professor at Case-Western Reserve for many years; Recipient of the Silver Medal of the Acoustical Society of America (1985) for "Pioneering research on the acoustics of brass and woodwind instruments and for leadership of a generation of musical acousticians" and the Gold Medal (1988) for "pioneering work in the science and art of musical acoustics, emphasizing the interactions among performer, instrument and listener." He was Vice-President of the ASA 74-75. In addition to his many papers in JASA, Art wrote two highly influential books: "Horns Strings and Harmony" (Dover, 1960) and "Fundamentals of Musical Acoustics." (Oxford 1976) He was a long-time member of the CAS and President 1969-72, and responsible for much of the thinking and progress in research of the Society. For many years he worked closely with J.C. Schelleng and C.M. Hutchins developing new theories and concepts in violin acoustics. See bio. in CASJ and his full files as part of this archive.
    Correspondence: (1961-1987) Principally CMH and AHB. Includes papers by others as enclosures requesting comment by one or other. (e.g. on vibrations of violin bridge by Rafferty and Lee); references to Nagavary (N1528) and Skudrzyk (S6295); copies of letters to AHB from JCS.